Hello everybody, my name
is Kyle Dixon. I'm one of
your 2026 academic medicine
scholars, teaching scholar.
Today we're going to be
going over GFR, renal
blood flow, and clearance
as a part of the renal
physiology section. I want
to thank Dr. Ascari for
helping me with this lecture,
letting me do it, as well
as revamping the entire
renal physiology section
for you guys. You guys are
lucky to have these lectures.
I also want to thank Dr.
Goldstein for helping
out and Brian Koflanovich
as well for helping out.
He's another scholar that's
working on this series.
So let's begin.
So my reason for doing
this lecture was because
renal physiology is a
very difficult topic, but
it's a very important
topic. The kidneys are
involved in basically all
homeostatic mechanisms.
Previous years, it's been tough
to convey this information
well, and I think what
Dr. Ascari is doing this
year is great, and I wanted
to help him out the best
I could. So on this slide
you can see some stuff about
me so on the left there
I'm with a emerald tree boa
they have the largest fangs
of any non venomous snake
I'm not gonna put that on
the exam don't worry but I
do research with dr. Molnar
involving snakes and I
love reptiles the top right
there that's me with my first
friend group in med school
from first year b6 I
still talk to them today
they help me with literally
everything rotations boards
and I highly recommend if you
can find a tight-net friend
group like that in school
it's gonna help you
immeasurably and then the bottom
right is probably my
favorite part of scholar year
so far which was teaching
neuroanatomy it was great
working with the faculty at
our school they were excellent
and then working with my
fellow scholars as well
and yeah let's move on to
the learning objectives and
a case i think a great
way to open up any medical
physiology lecture would to
just generally start with a
case study we're all going
to be future physicians
working in the medical field
and medicine is really patient
-centered so let's start
by looking at this patient
so which I want you to do
is to just pause the video
read the initial paragraph
read the test results and
then read the questions as
well and just start to think
about how you may want to
answer those questions the
point of this lecture is
going to be to go over
everything that you need to
know to basically answer this
question right here so if
you have some answers to the
things below or some
differentials you might be
thinking about it might be
smart to write those down now.
So I'm not going to be
reading these learning
objectives verbatim, but
to learn pathology, you
need to know physiology,
and to learn physiology,
you really need to
know anatomy. So we're
going to start with the
anatomy in this lecture,
which ties into the
blood flow of the kidney,
and that's the whole
purpose of this lecture.
There's going to be
many other lectures for
this renal series, but
mine is really on the
blood flow. Then we're
going to correlate that
with the kidney's ability
to alter physiology.
And then we're going
to finish off with that
case study that I already
mentioned, and then
we're going to go into
questions at the end.
Okay, let's start with
some anatomy review. So the
kidneys, they're located
below the diaphragm, and
they're retroperitoneal. So
what does that mean? They're
outside the peritoneum. so
they're basically attached
to the body cavity wall on
the back of the abdominal
cavity unlike the GI
organs which are mostly
within the peritoneum and
free-floating kidneys are
towards the back and basically
span the length of t12
to l3 with the right kidney
being lower than the left
because of the liver each
kidney there's two right
are being shaped with the
medial side called the hilum
containing blood vessels
and the ureters exiting.
They're both covered by a
dense elastic connective
tissue sheath called
the renal fascia.
It envelopes not only
the kidney but also the
suprarenal glands or
the adrenal glands. The
kidneys are deceptively
small which is kind of
a testament to how much
they do for the body.
The kidneys only take
up about 0.5 percent
of total body weight.
But despite this,
the blood flow through
them is massive.
I know you guys haven't
had cardio yet, but
cardiac output is heart
rate times stroke volume.
So the normal cardiac output
per minute is
about five liters.
The kidneys receive 20%
of this each minute, so
about one liter, which
once again is fascinating
considering how small
the organs are. You can
basically fit 150 cc's
of fluid in each kidney
so that would mean over
three times the amount
of that fluid flows
through them each minute.
You can see on the left
of this slide the entire
blood flow path to the
kidneys from the heart.
The major connection
between the kidneys and the
heart is the aorta with
the renal artery coming
off of the aorta. This
means that if there's any
damage to the aorta, the
kidneys can be affected.
Blood then flows
through the segmental
arteries and interlobal
arteries which
feed the individual
lobes of the kidney.
Arcuate arteries basically
encircle the kidney.
After the interlobular
arteries you then get to the
afferent arterial. This
is a very important
structure that we'll get
more into as the lecture goes
on. From there blood reaches
the glomerulus, which
we'll also get to, then
the afferent arteriole,
and then the peritubular
capillaries or vasa recta.
These encircle
the nephron or the
functional part of the kidney.
Interestingly, most blood
that reaches the kidney
stays in the cortex or
the outer part of it.
The blood stays in the
peritubular capillaries, but
about five to ten percent
of blood that reaches the
kidney goes to the salty
medulla which is the inner
part of the kidney. You
can see on that left figure
the vasorector all the way
on the bottom encircling
the thick and thin ascending
and descending limb.
I call the medulla salty
because it's a way for
me to remember that it's
highly concentrated and
this pattern of blood
flow keeps it that way.
But that also means that the
medulla is highly sensitive
to hypoxia and ischemic
damage. You will learn
later about acute tubular
necrosis, which basically
occurs because of this low
blood flow of the medulla.
Even in low blood flow
states, the cortex still gets
mostly enough oxygen, but
the medulla will suffer.
I know a lot of times we
don't talk about the venous
system, but here there's
some clinical correlates. So
the renal vein connects to
the inferior vena cava, and
if you remember from anatomy
the left renal vein is
longer because the left kidney
is further from the IVC.
Something called nutcracker
syndrome is a very rare
vascular compression
disorder where the left renal
vein is squeezed between
the abdominal aorta and
the superior mesenteric
artery which branches off
of the aorta. This is
once again due to it being
longer and having to cross
over to that left kidney.
This can lead to blood
in the urine, left flank
pain, pelvic pressure
pain, varicose veins in
the pelvis, and the
varicose seals which are
basically scrotal varicose
veins. It also has that
an extra connection of the
left gonadal vein which
makes varicose seals
more common on the left.
My lecture doesn't really
cover the functions of the
kidney or the functions of
nephron but I thought it
would be important to
include this slide because it
helped me study when I was
taking renal physiology.
This was created by
Isabel Artez, who
you saw on the Get
to Know You slide.
She was part of that B6 crew
I mentioned. The nephron
is the functional unit of
the kidney. It includes
the renal corpuscle, which
is the glomerulus, which
you see on the top, which
is a tuft of capillaries.
Bowman's capsule, which
is that mouth-looking
thing right next to the
glomerulus at the top.
And the rest is composed
of tubular cells. We break
down the nephron based on
sections. The first part
is the proximal convoluted
tubule. The second is the
lupahenle, which is broken
into the descending limb
and the ascending limb.
Then we move to the distal
convoluted tubule, and
finally the collecting duct.
If you see the bottom
left, I've mentioned
diuretics. The numbers
next to them correspond
on the actual nephron
where they act,
So feel free to come back to
this after you
learn about PHARM.
I've also put the renal
tubular acidosis and
where they occur by saying
RTA in different areas.
And I've even put
rare disorders like
Fanconi and Little
syndrome where they occur.
These are all board relevant.
In regards to
blood flow, like we
mentioned, we have the
afferent arteriole, so
the blood coming
into the glomerulus.
Then you have the glomerulus
itself, which is a tuft
of capillaries. and then
you have the efferent
arterial, which is leaving
the tuft of capillaries.
What you don't see here is
the peritubular capillaries
and the vasorector, which
both come off of the
efferent arterial, which I
mentioned on the last slide.
Once again, those peritubular
capillaries surround
the tubules in the cortex
to perform the active
reabsorption, whereas
the vasorector are in the
medulla and they preserve
that osmotic gradient.
and the vasorecta are
also the reason why
the medulla has that
low blood flow state.
Peritubular capillaries
stay in the cortex or the
top and vasorecta are in
the medulla or the middle.
So you would see the
vasorecta mostly where you see
those two loops of Henle
areas, so the descending
limb of the loop and the
ascending limb of the loop.
Just as an overview,
things that stay in this
tubular structure will
be urinated out. anything
that leaves would go back
into the bloodstream.
Like I said, this isn't
really the point of my
lecture to go over
anything on here, but I
thought it was important
and feel free to come back
to this when you cover
it in other lectures.
So we've looked at
the gross blood flow
anatomy, we've
looked at the nephron
itself, but what about
the renal corpuscle?
This is considered
the glomerulus, which
once again is a fancy
word for a tuft of
capillaries, and and
Bowman's capsule, which is
that mouth-looking
thing on the last slide.
Bowman's capsule is a
part of the nephron, where
the glomerulus is a
separate capillary network.
This is where
blood is able to be
filtered and
filtrate is formed.
This basically explains
how things in the
blood can get filtered
into the kidney,
reabsorbed, or excreted
out of the kidney in urine.
The glomerulus, once again,
is fed by that afferent
arteriole, A for afferent,
that's the blood coming in.
And then, after reaching
the glomerulus, it leads
to the efferent
arteriole, which then goes
into those peritubular
capillaries and vasorecta.
Bowman's capsule consists
of a double-walled
epithelial structure
enclosing the glomerulus.
and it consists
of simple squamous
epithelium on the parietal
layer and specialized
podocytes, which just
means foot processes,
with intergegiating
foot processes connected
by a slit diaphragm
on the visceral
layer, and it's interspersed
by some proteins.
We will cover this
more in depth later.
So picture like a net
that you use to grab
fish out of water. so
the net has to have
holes in it and there
has to be parts that let
things through or don't
let things through.
The net of the renal
corpuscle is what
you see on the
right two pictures.
So the middle is an actual
electron microscope image
and the one on the right
is just a cartoon example.
So anything getting from
the blood into the nephron
has to go past the capillary
endothelium, basement
membrane foot processes
and slit diaphragm of not
only the capillary at first
but then bowman's capsule
starting from the capillary
side you have that
fenestrated endothelium then
moving towards the bowman
space you have the
glomerular basement membrane
and then finally the
podocyte foot process is
the last thing the filtrate
will pass through The
entirety of the structure
is shown on the left.
You can see that transition
from the capillary
into the other side
of the Bowman space.
Also of note are mesangial
cells which are basically
macrophages and also
contractile to alter blood flow.
The sympathetic
nervous system has a
impact here which
we'll get into later.
And granular cells are the
same things as juxtaglomerular
cells so juxta just
means next to. These are
mechanoreceptive cells that
store and release renin, which
is part of the RAS system
to regulate blood pressure.
The macula densa is a
part of the tubular system
that senses sodium.
This is also in relation
to regulating blood
flow and blood pressure.
Interesting to note,
there's about 1 million
of these glomeruli and
nephrons per kidney.
as we age they decrease
which decreases kidney
function it's a very unique
system because it's arterial
to arterial where most
organ structures are
basically a artery then an
arterial a capillary network
a venule and then a vein
here we have the afferent
arterial the capillary
peritubular or vasorecta
and then we have the efferent
arterial so if you were
to remove a kidney you
would think that kidney
function would go down
proportionally 50% but actually
the remaining kidney can
sometimes hypertrophy.
The remaining kidney can
open up blood flow to itself
which we'll get into later
how it actually does that,
increasing its ability to
filter and perform its job.
So what's really the
physics behind renal
blood flow or blood
flow in general?
We use something called
Pusuli's Law and Ohm's Law.
You won't necessarily
have to do math on
exams or calculate
these, but it's good
to know the factors
that influence them.
So blood flow in
general is related
to change in pressure
over resistance.
Resistance is
related to the length
of the vessel, the
viscosity of the
blood, and the
radius of the vessel.
You could think of a
hose as an example,
just a standard water
hose. When you turn the
hose on, the water
flows throughout the
hose and then leaves
into the outside world.
Inside the hose is more
pressure than outside
the hose, pushing water
out. And that's that
delta P on the top of
the equation there for Q.
Now, resistance is
in the denominator.
Increasing resistance
will decrease Q or
blood flow or, in
this case, water flow.
So how do you
increase resistance?
you can lengthen the hose.
You can put something
more viscous in the
hose, maybe something
like milk or honey.
Both of those
factors will increase
resistance and decrease
flow of the water.
Decreasing resistance
will increase
the Q or the blood
flow or water flow.
So how would you do that?
You would increase the
radius of the hose. This is
very important. So radius
is to the fourth power.
In neither of these
equations, you would
see anything else with
that much influence.
So increasing or
decreasing radius basically
has the biggest impact
on any blood flow.
So changing the size
of the hose radius
outcompetes the length
of the hose, the pressure
difference, and pretty
much any viscosity.
The body is amazing, and
physiology is amazing.
so we've evolved to use
this to our advantage.
You can't really change
viscosity immediately,
you can't really change
length of vessels
immediately, but
radius can be changed,
vasoconstriction and
vasodilation. And the major region
for this in the kidney
is the afferent and the
efferent arteriole, which we
talked about. Changing these
parameters on these arteries
alter renal blood flow
blood pressure and the total
GFR now if you take the
blood flow equation Q equals
Delta P over R and you
solve for Delta P you get
R times Q equals change in
pressure this means that
vasoconstriction increases
blood pressure which is pretty
self-explanatory but what
isn't is how much that
actually affects the numbers
the heart must work harder
to get blood through a
constricted vessel. You see
on the right there in regards
to the heart and pressure
a 20% occlusion of a
healthy artery changes the
pressure from 120 milligrams
millimeters of mercury to
293 milligrams of mercury.
And only a 19%
decrease in radius of a
vessel will have the
volume flow rate.
So even small
alterations of dilation
and constriction can
have huge impacts,
which we'll see
with the kidney.
Once again, these
laws apply to any
vessel, but this is
a great way to start
to look at the
kidney specifically.
The figure on the right
is very important.
As blood travels
from the heart to the
aorta, down to the renal
artery, and eventually
into the smaller and
smaller arteries,
vascular resistance
increases because the vessels
are getting smaller. The
radius is decreasing.
Because of this sudden
change in radius,
pressure is basically backed
up into the larger arteries.
It's similar to like
a bottleneck effect.
Things before the bottleneck
have pressure build up
and things after them have
a decrease in pressure.
this is why as you go from
left to right on the graph
the pressure is decreasing
it's no coincidence that
the sites of largest vascular
resistance are the change
from the renal artery to
the aferin arterial and
the glomerular capillary
to the aferin arterial this
is because changing the
radius on these arterials has
a huge effect on blood
flow blood pressure and
physiology overall You saw
previously how small the glomerulus
was and how small the
afferent and efferent
arterials were. If they were
met with the same pressure
that the renal artery was
met with, they would burst.
This is why this large
vascular resistance is
necessary. As you might
remember from physics,
areas of high pressure move
to areas of low pressure.
Or more accurately,
things in a high-pressure
environment tend to move to
a low-pressure environment.
This is why I mentioned
in the first bullet
point there's net
filtration in the afferent
arterioles and glomerular
capillaries and
net reabsorption in the
peritubular capillaries.
This is why the
filterability can occur.
The afferent arterioles
and glomerular capillaries
have just enough pressure
to push out the things that
they need into the nephron
and into Bowman's space.
The peritubular
capillaries have that
decrease in pressure,
allowing them to
accept a higher
pressure environment.
Factors that influence
the relaxation or
constriction of the
afferent and efferent
arterios allow for sensitive
control of hydrostatic
pressure and the ability
to push molecules
and fluids into
different compartments.
If systemic blood pressure
goes up, the afferent
arterioles can constrict,
causing a larger drop in pressure
to keep the downstream
glomerular pressure stable.
A lot of times in renal
physiology and cardiovascular
physiology, they
use something called
MAP, which is mean
arterial pressure. This is
calculated by taking
systolic blood pressure plus
2 times diastolic blood
pressure divided by 3.
It gives a more accurate
measure of blood flow and
perfusion, and it gives
you basically the average
pressure within your arteries
during a single heartbeat.
So just as an example,
the normal map for an
adult human is 70 to 105
millimeters of mercury,
whereas in the afferent
arterial towards the
beginning, it's around 60 to
50 millimeters of mercury.
And that's where
the y-axis comes
from on that figure
on the right.
you can almost think of it
in an analogy to traffic
let's say you have a giant
highway with thousands
of cars and a single
exit ramp where only one
car at a time can get off
on the giant highway with
all those cars on it
have a large pressure
there's a lot of movement
there's changing lanes but
once you hit that bottleneck
similar to the aphron
arterial the one lane
cars can go only straight
and there's not much
movement and you lose some of
that energy and you lose
some of that pressure.
This diagram shows
perfectly what
I just explained
on the last slide.
From left to right you
have the renal artery
pressure, then the efferent
arterial resistance, then
glomerular capillary
pressure, then efferent
arterial resistance, and
then peritubular capillary
pressure. You notice renal
artery pressure is at
that map I talked about.
It's pretty much at 100.
But glomerular
capillary pressure is
altered depending on
resistance in both
the afferent and
efferent arterial.
Increasing that resistance
by vasoconstricting,
as you see on the 1.5,
so the second one down,
creates that bottleneck
effect I was talking about
where the renal artery
pressure stays at 100, but
then the glomerular
capillary pressure drops down
to 40 from 60. This decreased
pressure in the glomerular
capillary will affect
the ability for that area
to push fluid and
electrolytes into the nephron.
Now on the reverse, when
you have a relaxation
of the aferin arterial,
so the bottom row,
glomerular capillary
pressure increases because
you're having more
flow into the area. Now
as you see in both, the
aferin arterial is doing
the reverse of what the
afferent arterial is
doing. This further
accentuates the process.
However in some
scenarios they may go a
similar way so maybe the
afferent and the efferent
are both working in
the same direction.
I want to mention too that
each glomerulus in the
million about a million
nephrons of each kidney could
be doing different things.
Not all of them have to be
doing the same thing when
it comes to the afferent
arterial resistance and
efferent arterial resistance.
Your body's
constantly adapting to
changing fluid
levels, what you eat,
things you consume, and fluid
levels as well. So usually
when I'm talking about
this stuff, it's just
considering one nephron at a
time or glomerulus at a time.
Now I want to talk
about regular blood flow
versus renal blood flow
versus renal plasma flow.
This can be a little confusing.
Q, which we already
talked about, deals with
the specific hemodynamics
within the vessels of
the kidney or any other
artery. While total
renal blood flow deals
with the actual full volume
of blood reaching the
kidney specifically.
And renal plasma flow
is the renal blood
flow minus the cells
within the blood.
So cell-free
plasma each minute.
renal blood flow is a great
measure of overall oxygen
and nutrient delivery to
the kidneys renal plasma
flow looks actually at the
filterable fluid the kidneys
will get per minute hematocrit
is the percent of total
blood volume that consists
of red blood cells so
men normally have 41 to 50
percent and female normally
36 to 47 percent children
can be variable depending
on age. Anemia, this number
would be low. In something
like polycythemia or
dehydration, it would be high.
Since hematocrit is
percent of RBCs, then one
minus hematocrit is
approximately blood plasma
percentage. These are
all approximations.
Hematocrit, like I
already mentioned,
relates to the blood
viscosity, so the
N factor from the
Q formula earlier.
Increase in hematocrit
means basically more RBCs,
which increases viscosity
and increases in resistance
and a decrease in overall
flow through the kidneys. So
you can see how some
pathological processes might
impact this. So that's why
finding renal plasma flow
would be taking the renal
blood flow times the percentage
of one minus hermetocrine,
because that's going
to be the percentage of
blood that just contains the
plasma and then you just
divide the term over to find
the renal blood flow from
the renal plasma flow i
don't think you would have
to really calculate any of
these numbers on an exam
but it's good to know the
relationships the normals
are about one liter a minute
for renal blood flow like
i mentioned on the first
slide and then renal plasma
flow is about 600 to 650
milliliters a minute. The
term effective is basically a
term that is looking at a
marker that is estimated.
In studies this can be
found using something
called para-aminohyperic
acid or PAH.
This is due to the fact
that PAH in plasma is almost
fully excreted out of
the kidney into urine.
So it gets filtered in
and then it stays in the
tubule and then is peed
out. Meaning that its renal
plasma flow is basically
equal to its clearance.
So as much that's in the
plasma goes into the kidney,
into the bladder, and
then it's urinated out.
The clearance of PAH is found
by multiplying the urine
flow rate times the
concentration of PAH in the
urine divided by the
concentration of PAH in the blood.
or plasma.
We will come back to clearance.
In the modern day, you
can use radioactive
tracers in syntigraphy to
find renal plasma flow.
These are important topics
clinically and also
on board exams.
So taking in everything
we just learned and
then moving on to
glomerular filtration,
I wanted to give you guys
some stats about what
happens every day in the
kidney. So So cardiac
output, like I said, per
minute is about 5 liters.
That's how much
the heart pumps.
Now 20% of this, or 1
liter, reaches the kidneys,
which you can convert to
about 1,000 milliliters.
So 400 milliliters of
this is unfilterable,
which we'll get into
what kind of things are
unfilterable. So usually
those are like large
substances like red
blood cells or albumin.
And 600 milliliters
of this 1,000
constitutes plasma
that can be filtered.
But only about 20% of
this plasma actually
gets filtered into
Bowman's space.
So if you convert
that, then it's 120
milliliters a minute
that's filtered.
So to find the daily
amount, there's about
1440 minutes a day.
You take 1440 times 120
milliliters, and you
get 172,800 milliliters.
So about 173 liters a day
of plasma is filtered into
the tubules of the kidney.
Wow, isn't that amazing?
But you might be
thinking to yourself,
do we pee 173
liters a day? I hope
you don't because
that would be crazy.
So obviously not.
The actual amount that
we urinate out is about 1
.73 liters or 1% of this.
So what happened then?
About 99% of things that
are filtered through
the kidney are reabsorbed
back into the blood.
So plasma volume equates
to around 3 liters total.
So that means this volume
is filtered about 60
times a day. So all of
that plasma is filtered
about 60 times a day.
Pretty amazing stuff.
So when we talk
about filtration,
things can get
terminology heavy.
So this slide goes over
what everything means.
Like I said, only
about 1% of things that
actually get filtered
end up in the urine.
This diagram on the
left is everything
that basically happens
within the nephron
and the vasculature
in a nutshell.
Excretion is just another
term for urination.
So excretion then would
equal the things that are
filtered through into the
nephron minus the things
that are brought back into
the blood or reabsorbed.
and the things
secreted to stay within
the tubules and
eventually excreted.
Things that are reabsorbed
and secreted have to be
filtered first, but the
difference is one thing goes
back into the blood and one
thing stays in the urine.
We talked about the
pressures of the afferent
arterioles and glomerular
capillaries. This is what drives
the formation of the
ultrafiltrate or filtrate,
and that just means the fluid
that's left after things
come from the blood and
go into the actual tubular
system. You see that
glomerular filtrate fluid
left after the ultrafiltration
occurs. We touched
upon clearance which is
the rate at which substance
is removed from the body
by the kidney and put into
urine to be excreted.
This is going to be the
concentration of whatever
substance in urine times the
urine flow rate divided by
the plasma concentration.
GFR or glomerular filtration
rate is expressed in
milliliters a minute, and
it's the actual volume
of fluid filtered from
the blood by the kidneys
glomeruli into the kidney
tubules per unit of time.
It is the number one
indicator of kidney function.
To get actual GFR, you
would need to do a 24
-hour urine test, but in
the clinic, most people
use eGFR, which is a
blood test for creatinine
levels. I've linked the
resources you can use to
calculate this in different
people on rotations.
Okay, so by now we've
talked about the blood
flow to the kidney,
how the blood flow is
regulated, what factors
influence the blood
flow, as well as some
filtration definitions,
but what actually is
being filtered and what
influences the ability
to be filtered or not.
So first we'll talk
about what's in the blood
that will reach the
renal corpuscle, what
barriers exist, which we
already kind of touched
on, and what are the
underlying pressures
in physics behind why
things get filtered.
So things that are in the
blood that will filter freely
are small, positively
charged, inorganic molecules.
And they basically share
a similar concentration
in filtrate to the blood,
meaning they filter freely.
These include electrolytes
like sodium and chloride,
glucose, amino acids, urea,
creatine, and vitamins.
Anything that's large,
negatively charged, and a
blood cell will not
usually filter freely. What
we're referring to here
is physiologic conditions.
In many pathological
conditions,
you'll see this
gets interrupted.
Please take a moment to look
at the chart on the right.
You'll notice something like
sodium is filtering very
freely, whereas something
like albumin really has
no shot of getting through
the filter barrier in a
physiologic state you'll
notice too that sodium and
potassium filter more freely
than chloride because of
their positive charge even
though they're basically
the same size so the three
barriers to filtration
we already covered on an
earlier slide but i'll go
through them again because
it's important so on the
capillary side of the glomerulus
you have the fenestrated
endothelial cells these
are size exclusive they
only allow things under 100
nanometers to fit through
them the basement membrane
basically separates the
capillary side from the
bowman space side it contains
type 4 collagen heparin
sulfate glycoproteins and
proteoglycans it is
negatively charged this is
electromagnetic exclusion
negative things repel negative
things so that this is why
the barrier repels negative
charges closer to The
Bowman space is the visceral
epithelialator with the
podocyte foot processes.
These once again are size
exclusive and usually
they have to be less
than 50 nanometers.
Slit diaphragms also
occur here which are just
basically slits to allow
small things to pass by.
This is once again our net.
Many different nephrotic
and nephritic syndromes
attack these areas of
the filtration barrier.
For example, diseases
against type 4 collagen
can affect the ability
for kidneys to filter.
So what is actually
driving this filterability?
You have hydrostatic
and oncotic pressure.
Hydrostatic pressure
is basically a pressure
exerted by a fluid at
rest due to gravity.
So more fluid and
more blood pressure
means higher
hydrostatic pressure.
Oncotic pressure is a pulling
pressure that is enacted
by large molecules particularly
proteins like albumin
in the blood. This pressure
is one of the reasons
fluid doesn't just leave
arteries and veins in the body.
The combination of these
determines the GFR or filter
ability of this sequence.
Please look at the formula
on the bottom there. So
some things want to move the
fluid into Bowman space and
some things want to take
it out of Bowman space back
into the capillary. Things
that favor filtration are
the hydrostatic pressure in
the glomerular capillaries
as GC and the oncotic
pressure of the filtrate in
the Bowman space, which I will
make a note is very small
because I just mentioned
that large proteins that
usually exert an oncotic
pressure aren't supposed to
be found in the Bowman space.
Things that work against
filterability are the
hydrostatic pressure
in Bowman space and the
oncotic pressure in the
glomerular capillary.
K sub F is a glomerular
permeability value.
It is under active
control and it
differs between organ to organ.
The summation and
combination of all of these
factors, whether they
oppose or favor filtration,
will determine the
actual filterability
of the fluid passing
through the glomerulus.
These usually aren't
calculated clinically,
but we'll get to
that later, how
GFR is actually
looked at clinically.
This slide is to
further show the
importance of these pressures.
On the right, the
first thing I noticed
was the lack of
oncotic pressure in
Bowman's space, like
I already mentioned.
I had a teacher in ninth
grade that used to say
molecules will naturally
flow from an area of high
to low. So if you look at
the fluid or hydrostatic
pressures of the
glomerular capillary blood
versus the fluid pressure
in Bowman space, it's 60
versus 15. The fluid's
going to want to flow
from the 60 to the 15. So
from the PGC to the PBS.
You still do have
that albumin in the
plasma and that's
where that 29 comes
from, which is noted
with a pi symbol.
You can start thinking
about now changes in
blood pressure and changes
in protein content of
the blood may have an
effect on these numbers.
The net filtration pressure
is a positive number
here at 16, meaning that
things will be flowing from
the glomerular capillary
into the Bowman space.
On the left is an
image from First
Aid, which also
shows this very well.
You can even see some of
the words I mentioned,
excreted, secreted,
reabsorbed, and filtered,
as well as some
effects of some drugs
like ACE inhibitors
or NSAIDs, which
will be covered
in other lectures.
It is very important to always
remember which pressures
are driving filtration
and which are against it.
So here's some more
filtration formulas to know.
Like already mentioned,
GFR is best estimated with
creatinine clearance in
urine, but clinically we use
EGFR, which is estimated
with blood creatinine levels.
RPF is best estimated
with PAH clearance, which
once again is the urine
flow rate times the urine
concentration divided by
plasma concentration. So
filtration fraction, which
is the GFR over the RPF or
clearance of creatinine
over clearance of PAH,
indicates what percentage
of renal plasma is filtered
into the Bowman's capsule.
So normally it's about
20% like I already mentioned
or one fifth of the
plasma entering the kidneys
is really filtered. It
helps identify changes
in kidney blood flow and
glomerular function. In specific
scenarios like dehydration
or a pathology called
renal artery stenosis,
GFR is maintained but RPF
will decrease causing an
increase in filtration
fraction. In scenarios of
glomerular disease where
the kidney can't keep up and
GFR falls and the renal
plasma flow stays the same,
you would see a decrease
in filtration fraction.
Filtered load is just GFR
times the plasma concentration
of some substance, such
as sodium or glucose.
It's the amount of
substance filtered into the
nephron each We can use
this to see how much of a
substance is reabsorbed,
secreted, or excreted. For
example, if you have a
GFR of 125 milliliters a
minute and a plasma glucose
of 1 milligram per milliliter,
the filtered load would
just be 125 times 1,
and if all 125 milligrams
a minute are reabsorbed,
no glucose would then
appear in the urine. So
if the filtered load
exceeds the kidney's
reabsorptive capacity,
capacity, glucose appears in
the urine, as can occur
in diabetes mellitus.
So if you're filtering
more than what the kidneys
can keep up with, things
are going to start showing
up in the urine,
especially things that can
pass through that filtration
barrier like glucose.
The plant protein inulin is the
gold standard for GFR testing.
It does not bind to plasma
proteins. it is a hundred
percent freely filtered
through the kidney it never
gets reabsorbed and it's
never secreted and 0% of it
is synthesized degraded or
stored in the body because
it comes from a plant so why
isn't this used clinically
if it's such a perfect
marker for GFR and clearance
because it isn't naturally
produced by the human
body to actually perform an
inulin clearance test, you
would need a continuous IV
infusion and timed urine
collection, which could be
burdensome and expensive.
In more clinical
research settings, it
can be used, but
in daily clinical
practice, it would
be not smart to use.
I actually misspoke, so
inulin is not a protein,
it's a polysaccharide, but
that doesn't change much.
While inulin is the
gold standard, for the
reasons I've explained,
we tend to use creatinine.
Creatinine is the closest
endogenous substance to inulin.
It's predictably
produced at a constant
rate in the body. It's
freely filtered by
the kidneys, and it's
neither reabsorbed
nor significantly
metabolized in the body.
You may hear a lot of people
say creatine when they're
talking about kidney
function, but they're actually
wrong. We're talking
about creatinine here.
Creatinine is a waste product
of daily muscle breakdown
where creatine is an energy
source the body produces
and can be increased by
dietary supplementation.
You may know some people
or some friends who
go to the gym and take
creatine supplementation
to improve strength
and muscle endurance.
Normal serum creatine
is between 0.74 and 1.35
milligrams per deciliter
for men and 0.59 to 1.04
milligrams per deciliter per
woman this all depends on
muscle mass and lab standards
once again just to note
the clearance and GFR for
creatinine would be needed
to use a urine sample over
24 hours but estimated
GFR eGFR is when you take
the actual blood sample
for serum creatine
creatinine and because it's a
muscle mass breakdown product,
muscle mass, age, diet,
and activity all can
influence it in minor ways.
It actually isn't perfect
like inulin is, and it
does slightly overestimate
GFR, but it is one of
the best markers we have.
A newer biomarker is
Cystatin C, which is an
alternative endogenous
marker, and it's produced
by all nucleated cells,
but it's less influenced
by muscle mass or diet.
However, they're finding
it can be influenced
more by thyroid
disease, diabetes, and
smoking. So if a substance
has a clearance and
GFR that are 100% equal,
it's something like
inulin, and it's not
secreted or reabsorbed.
If clearance is greater
than GFR, this is something
similar to creatinine,
and there would be
a net secretion of this
substance, substance X.
If GFR is higher
than clearance, that
would mean there would
be a net reabsorption
of X or it's not
freely filtered.
I forgot to mention on the
last slide why creatinine
clearance runs slightly
higher than the estimated
EGFR. Because the kidneys
themselves secrete a very
small amount of extra
creatinine into the urine
through the renal tubules.
This is why creatine clearance,
creatinine clearance, is
slightly more high than
an EGFR derived from a
blood test of creatinine.
This slide, I wouldn't
memorize this, but this is
just the biochemical pathway
of getting from amino
acids to creatine to
creatinine. So just to nail
it into your head that
there are two different
things, creatine and
creatinine. And I know I
misspoke here and there,
but I hope you guys get it.
So why is any of
this important?
Basically, EGFR is a major
factor in looking at kidney
function. And as physicians,
we're going to see
patients who have different
pathologies, patients on
different medications, and we
have to adjust the treatments
using those medications
and how we look at the
pathologies based on how
their kidneys are functioning.
I've linked on the top left
two great resources you
can use on rotations to
determine GFR and clearance.
And it is actually good
to know for exam purposes
the different stages of
chronic kidney disease,
because they will give
you symptomatology and how
the patients are doing
and expect you to know the
difference between stage 4
and stage 2, for example.
Permanent kidney failure
and dialysis is a serious
thing. I know loved
ones affected by it, and
it truly is life-altering.
So if you can maintain
health and maintain
good kidney health, that
would definitely benefit
you in the long run.
This is a clinical
correlate from a book called
Clinical Pathophysiology
Made Ridiculously
simple. It's cheap, it's on
Amazon, I highly recommend
it. The point I'm trying
to make here is that
in any type of renal
failure or renal damage,
you're going to see an
increase in creatinine.
Further studies are
needed to nail down what
kind of renal failure
might be occurring.
So for example, if there's
an insult to the blood
supply of the kidney, such
as in pre-renal failure,
remember we talked about
the renal arteries and all
the blood vessels that
supply the kidney. Let's
say there's an insult there.
The kidney freaks out.
It thinks that the body as
a whole doesn't have enough
fluid and sodium because
it's not getting fed with
blood. So what happens is it
sequesters all the sodium,
keeps it in the body.
Sodium excretion goes down.
Urine sodium is down. And
this overall decrease in fluid
flow through the kidney
gives the kidney basically
more time to reabsorb a lot
of things, including urea.
This lack of fluid and
hypovolemia that the
kidney senses makes it
want to hold on to more
fluid and water, and
urea basically follows.
But like we mentioned,
creatinine is not reabsorbed.
So that's why the serum BUN
to creatinine ratio is greater
than 20 to 1. The kidney
can work fine. It just
isn't receiving that adequate
blood supply. And like I
said, this could be an
insult to the arteries, or it
could be something like
dehydration or congestive heart
failure, which you guys will
get into much more later.
But at this level,
the take-home message
is the serum creatinine
went up, and that's
a sign of non-specific
kidney insult.
So up to this
point, we've covered
the anatomy of
the renal system,
especially blood
supply, filtration,
the cortex versus the medulla.
We've looked at the
correlation between the anatomy
and the functions, such
as with GFR, resistance,
blood pressure, hydrostatic
and oncotic pressure, as
well as the filtration
barriers. Now I want to get
into autoregulation and
the vasoactive substance
influences on the kidney.
As we age, as we get sick,
as we succumb to injury,
as we exercise, as we have
different availability of
food and water, our body's
internal dynamics change.
But like any other organ
system in the body, we want
to maintain homeostasis.
So the kidney's way of
doing this is to support a
constant GFR and renal blood
flow despite changes in
perfusion pressure. So
even in times of low blood
flow, the kidney should
still be able to reabsorb 99
% of that fluid that comes
through and electrolytes
that come through and excrete
that 1% that need to get
out of the body. So how
does the kidney adapt is
really what autoregulation
is. You can see the two
and third bullet points go
over some situations that
the kidney is trying to
avoid. And there's basically
three main mechanisms to
counteract these changes.
There's the myogenic
mechanism, an innate smooth
muscle tone, the macula
densa cells, which are
chemoreceptors and the
JG cells or granular
cells, which are
mechanoreceptors in relation to
the tubuloglomerular
feedback mechanism, as well
as influence from the
autonomic nervous system.
The myogenic mechanism
refers to the ability of
the afferent and efferent
arterials of the kidney
to vasodilate and
vasoconstrict. This is why the
opening physiology I went
over is very important.
In times of high blood
pressure and too much
flow to the kidney, the
afferent arterial can stretch
and feel this change.
In response to this, it
vasoconstricts, creating
that bottleneck effect.
This decreases
incoming renal blood
flow and proportionally
decreases GFR,
maintaining a filtration
fraction of normal.
If the opposite is
true, in a low broad
pressure setting, there's
a decrease in stretch
in the afferent
arterial, which triggers
it to vasodilate,
increasing RBF and GFR.
These are responses
to high perfusion
and low perfusion,
respectively.
Another way to sense
this is sodium.
The macula densa is a
group of cells found in
the straight distal
tubule of the nephron.
They are chemoreceptors
sensing sodium levels.
In times of high perfusion
and high sodium content,
The macula densa signals
this, and it basically
says, wow, we have an
increased GFR signal here. In
response, ATP and thromboxane
A2 can be released.
This constricts the afferent
arterial, decreasing
GFR and decreasing RBF,
similar to the myogenic
mechanism for an increase
in blood pressure.
Mirroring that of a
decreased perfusion or
decreased blood pressure,
Low sodium transport
to the macula denser will
decrease GFR signals,
increasing prostaglandin
and renin release.
This causes afferent dilation,
increase in GFR,
and increase in RBF.
If I haven't talked about
it yet, anything that
constricts the afferent
arterial will decrease GFR.
Anything that vasodilates
it will increase GFR. The
reverse is true for the
efferent arterial. Anything that
vasoconstricts the efferent
arteriole will increase
GFR. Anything that vasodilates
the efferent arteriole
will decrease GFR. You
always have to be thinking of
the glomerulus in the middle
of these two arterioles.
Anything that increases
that pressure between
the two arterioles will
increase GFR because
it's increasing that
hydrostatic pressure.
If you need to, go back to
that last slide of where I
showed the different changes
in the numbers of the
afferent and efferent arterials
depending on their tone.
I almost like to think
about it like you're
trapping blood in that
glomerular capillary bed.
For example, if you're opening
just the afferent arterial
or if you're closing just
the efferent arterial,
you're trapping blood in
that middle space, increasing
pressure there and pushing
for that increase in GFR,
and the reverse is true if
you want it to decrease GFR.
On the left is the
response to low perfusion.
Low perfusion, the sympathetic
neurons are activated.
There's a decreased arterial
pressure in the aferin
arterial, and the macula
densa might be sensing low
sodium. This can trigger the
JG cells, which stimulate
renin release from them, and
then you get into the RAS
pathway, which will be covered
heavily in another lecture,
but I'm just going to touch
upon it a little later
too. On the right is just
some other scenarios. For
example, the NA delivery to
the macula densa will stimulate
the ATP release, which
is actually a vasodilator
in this setting, of the
efferent arteriole and
vasoconstrictor of the efferent
arteriole. So this is going
over that third mechanism,
the nervous system's input.
On On the top we have
some very high yield
DO friendly viscerosomatics
and Chapman points.
These are a must know
for the level 1 and
level 2 and level 3
exams for DO students.
Then on the bottom is a topic
that usually isn't covered
too much in detail, but
it's the sympathetic or
fight or flight nervous
system's effect on the kidneys.
In times of stress, fight
or flight, or times of low
perfusion, such in pathologies
like congestive heart
failure, the sympathetic
nervous system is activated. And
you see on the left and
right, the activation is very
similar. There's low blood
pressure sensed in the
internal carotid arteries,
the carotid sinus baroreceptor
activity decreases, and the
sympathetic nerves of the
sympathetic chain ganglular
of T10 to T11 release
norepinephrine. Now, on
the left side is the direct
effects, and the right side
is the indirect effects.
Directly, this stimulates
the alpha-1 receptors,
and as you may remember,
this is a GQ mechanism with
calcium, causing
vasoconstriction of the afferent
arterial and efferent
arterial, but more of the
afferent arterial. As we
already mentioned, when
you do this, decreases renal
blood flow and decreases
GFR, because you're
creating that bottleneck.
Indirectly, norepinephrine
can interestingly bind
to the juxtaglomerular
cells or granular cells.
These cells contain
B1 receptors.
This triggers the RAS
cascade and the release of
renin. This once again
leads to vasoconstriction.
So why is this important?
Why are we decreasing blood
flow to the kidney during
sympathetic activation?
Because in times of stress,
the last thing we need
to worry about is filtering
blood and making urine.
We want blood flow to
the muscles and the
more vital organs for
fighting or flighting.
So like the heart, lungs,
and the skeletal muscle.
But in chronic times of
sympathetic activation,
like once again in
congestive heart failure,
this decrease in
blood flow to the
kidney can be very detrimental.
This is once again
some responses of
the body to differing
renal perfusions.
ADH is anti-duretic hormone,
also known as vasopressin,
which is released by
the posterior pituitary
in conjunction with control
by the hypothalamus.
It helps the body
hold on to water in
times of decreased
baroreceptor activity.
Renin, once again, is part
of that RAS system, and
that will be activated in
any times that the kidney
senses a low perfusion or
low body fluid volume to
increase blood pressure. I
wanted to give you guys an
overview of vasoactive
substances. So vasoactive just
means that they either
vasoconstrict or vasodilate.
So here we're referring to
the kidney specifically.
Some things to mention is
rena once again is that
starting cascade of the RAS
pathway. It's stored by JG
cells and released in
conjunction with decreased
perfusion and a sense of low
blood pressure in the body.
angiotensin 2 is a huge
player in the RAS system
and it preferentially
constricts the efferent
arteriole in the kidneys
because of greater
at1 receptor amounts in
the efferent arteriole
what would this do the GFR
usually should increase
it right because you're
constricting that last
part and increasing the
pressure in the glomerular
capillary bed atp here
while it's usually an
energy molecule, it
actually works in the
juxtaglomerular feedback
mechanism to vasoconstrict.
Only high-dose
dopamine vasoconstricts
because when you get
over a certain amount
of it, it activates
the alpha-1 receptors
on the afferent and
afferent arterioles.
Cocaine and meth also
affect the kidney, damaging
it by creating this
vasoconstriction, as they do
in other arteries of the
body and blood vessels.
Some vasodilasers are
the prostaglandins.
They almost act as
like a shield for the
kidney for low blood
flow and ischemia. They
just relax everything,
the prostaglandins.
Nitric oxide kind of acts as
a maintaining vasodilator.
Without it, there would
be non-stop constriction.
ANP and BNP work almost
against antidiuretic
hormone, which i mentioned
in the last slide they
want you to get rid of
excess water in the body
once again low dose dopamine
is a vasodilator because
it only acts on d1 and d2
receptors not alpha receptors
so you could start to
think with these questions
on the bottom how giving
certain medications or doing
certain things would affect
the vasoconstriction ability
and vasodilation capabilities
of the kidney so this
is the big bad brass system
like I mentioned Brian
is going to cover this in
detail within his lecture but
I just wanted to give you
a nice little diagram about
it just as a taste I
think it's always good to
remember this whole system
works based on a drop in blood
pressure and a drop in fluid
volume once you realize
that if it's being activated
you can kind of use that
to guess the physiology or
interpret the physiology.
For example, angiotensin
2 acts directly
on blood vessels stimulating
vasoconstriction.
Like we talked about,
decreasing the radius of
a vessel will increase its
pressure. The body has
sensed that it has a drop in
blood pressure, so it wants
to increase that pressure.
Sodium and water act to
increase blood pressure,
so eventually in the RAS
system something called
aldosterone is released
and it stimulates the
reabsorption of sodium in
water. It all makes sense.
This is one of the most
high-yield physiological
mechanisms that they love
to ask questions about and
it's super important to
know for clinical practice.
ACE inhibitors and ARBs
are constantly being given
out to people with high
blood pressure and the
reason is right here this
isn't a pathology lecture
but I just wanted to make
a list of things that
can affect what we went
over today I would suggest
copying pasting everything
on this slide and maybe
just putting it into AI
and asking AI how does
this affect renal blood
flow GFR and basically the
why behind that okay
let's get back to the case
so this patient is suffering
from diabetic nephropathy
and because of chronic
hyperglycemia due to
not following medications
the glomeruli are
basically damaged in the
kidney interesting to note
in early disease there
this actually causes
glomerular hyperfiltration
and gfr actually initially
increases not decreases
this is due to sugar
activating the efferent
arterioles to dilate and an
increase in the glomerular
capillary pressure.
So non-enzymatic
glycosylation occurs,
the glomerular basement
membrane thickens,
misangiocells proliferate and
deposit excess
extracellular matrix,
podocytes actually
become damaged and
are lost, and you
lose that filtration
membrane or net that
we talked about.
Albubin begins to leak
into the tubules and urine,
sclerosis of the
glomerular lie occur and
there's actually nephron
loss over time leading to
chronic kidney disease.
Renal biopsy would show
glomerular basement
membrane thickness actually,
mesangial expansion,
and diffuse glomerular
sclerosis. Something called
Kimmelstein-Wilson
nodules can form as well.
Like I mentioned initially
there's an increase
in GFR but then due to
nephron loss and glomerular
loss, GFR just plummets.
Because of that initial
afferent dilation, you
get that increase in
pressure in the area,
increase in sugar in the
area, and it damages the
whole filtration system.
Interestingly too, so you
have this proteinuria and
albuminuria in the urine,
so albumin in the urine. So
you're losing protein out
of the blood. And like we
talked about, protein is
a sieve that acts with
oncotic pressure so usually
the albumin in the blood keeps
fluid within the vessels
of the body but now you're
losing all that albumin
and urine so what happens
fluid can move away from
the intravascular space and
move into the
intersitial tissues
so and outside of
the vasculature
interestingly to increase
glucose reabsorption in
the proximal tubule reduces
sodium delivery to the
macula densa. So the macula
densa is like, oh, we're
getting no sodium. Let's
increase the tubuloglomerular
feedback mechanism and
activate RAS. And this
is that chronic sympathetic
-esque activation I
talked about. You're
maintaining that intraglomerular
pressure and worsening
kidney damage over time. So
what could have prevented
this blood pressure control
tight blood glucose
control something like an
sgl t2 inhibitor or something
like an ace inhibitor
or arb could help you want
to decrease hypertension
and you want to decrease
the hyperglycemia regular
exercise normal healthy
habits smoking cessation
and then eating a diet low
in sodium egfr should have
been monitored serum
creatinine electrolytes and
urine albumin should be monitored
as well. We must counsel
patients like this on drug
use and avoiding certain
medications such as NSAIDs
because they're nephrotoxic.
And then you would also
have to talk about the
consequences of dialysis
or kidney transplantation.
You want to slow
that declining GFR.
These next two slides
are just practice
questions from the
textbook. they're not really
board style or a style
that you'll see on
your exam but they're
a good gauge for how
well you understand the
content we went over.
I highly recommend doing them.
What you'll find as you
move through second year and
you get to board studying
is that questions are
necessary to learn any of
this information. So I highly
recommend you do these and
you can check yourself by
looking up the answers if
you need in the textbook.
Please email me or Dr. Ascari
if you have any questions.
We're now on to the board-style
questions I made.
There are six.
I want you to pause
the video right now,
go through them, work
on them yourself, and
then I'll give you the
answers at the end.
So when some people
do these questions,
they like to read
the actual question
first, so the last
sentence, basically.
I don't find that helpful
for myself. I usually
like to look at patient
demographics first and then
physical exam findings
and focus on labs as well.
try to always look for
what is important in
the question because
there's going to be a
lot of distractors
especially they love to
do that on the boards
here's four and five
okay so the answers are
cac bbb so number one
was tying the effects
of nsaids decreasing
prostaglandins to
hydrostatic pressure and gfr
trying to get you guys
to think about how nsaids
nephrotoxic so that's
why it was c decrease in
the hydrostatic pressure
and decrease in gfr
number two the purpose
wasn't really the
calculation it was the
the determining of what
to calculate so the
hydrostatic pressure right we
said filters favors filtration
the other two factors
there filter moving fluid
the other way from bowman's
to the glomerular capillary
so you have to know what
to subtract there and
that's why you get A is 10.
Number three is a woman
suffering from a panic
attack. Choices A, B, and
E really revolve around the
RAS system which is in
response to low perfusion
and low pressure so those
wouldn't be the answer.
Here her map rose from
90 to 130 so the two main
mechanisms we talked about
in relation to that would be
the tubular gomeric feedback
and myogenic response.
You could argue that
the sympathetics would
also increase but this
is asking how the body
is keeping the GFR
and renal blood flow
relatively stable and
GFR. So the answer is C.
Number four was just testing
your knowledge about the
vasoactive substances. So we
were looking for angiotensin
2 and what does angiotensin
2 do in regards to
the afferent and efferent
arterial it preferably constricts
the efferent increasing
the capillary hydrostatic
pressure and increasing gfr
number five is describing
hemorrhagic shock and
sympathetic overdrive so that's
why the answer is b the
rest don't really make sense
number six you may have
struggled with because you
didn't have this lecture
yet but anytime a question
mentions hemoptysis, linear
immunofluorescent staining,
definitely think of
Goodpasture syndrome,
which is the syndrome I
was talking about when we
went over the netting that
is an anti-type 4 collagen
antibody syndrome. This
disrupts the glomerular basal
membrane and the middle
layer of the filtration
barrier, allowing for blood
in the urine, dark urine,
fatigue, and hemoptysis.
While Goodpasture does have
the hemoptysis it doesn't
have the chronic sinusitis
nosebleeds and saddle
nose deformity that something
like GPA would have.
Okay I hope you guys enjoyed
my lecture a few tips for
studying for this information
would be using multiple
resources so in conjunction
with this lecture maybe
using boards and beyond
YouTube videos are also great
dirty medicine has a great
series online and then things
like the first aid book
really helped me when I was
studying this information
as well I think hearing it
from multiple different
perspectives is always helpful.
And if you have any
questions, feel free to email
me and I'll see you guys
in the GI block next
semester where I'm
going to present some GI
parasites to you guys. So
I wish you guys luck the
rest of this semester and
I hope to see you soon.